<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-lm-spring-srv6-generalized-arguments-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Generalized Arguments">Generalized Arguments of SRv6
    Segment</title>

    <author fullname="Zhenbin Li" initials="Z. " surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>lizhenbin@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jianwei Mao" initials="J. " surname="Mao">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>MaoJianwei@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C. " surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="July" year="2022"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document analyzes the challenges of Arguments of SRv6 SID, and
      the chance of using Arguments of SRv6 SID to reduce the length of the
      IPv6 extension header. According to these analysis, this document
      specifies a kind of generalized and structured Arguments for SRv6 SID,
      which can carry multiple Arguments parts for a SRv6 SID.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document analyzes the challenges of the Arguments of SRv6 SID,
      and the chance of using Arguments of SRv6 SID to reduce the length of
      the IPv6 extension header. According to these analysis, this document
      specifies a kind of generalized and structured arguments for SRv6 SID,
      which can carry multiple Arguments parts for a SRv6 SID.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref> <xref target="RFC8174">RFC
      8174</xref> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown
      here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminologies">
      <t>SRv6: Segment Routing over IPv6</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Problem Statement and Requirements">
      <t>With the development of SRv6, several kinds of SRv6 Arguments for the
      SRv6 End SID and End.X SID emerge<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-srh-compression"/>, including:</t>

      <t>1. SRv6 C-SID compression (NEXT Flavor): using Arguments to carry
      multiple C-SIDs.</t>

      <t>2. SRv6 C-SID compression (REPLACE Flavor): using Arguments to carry
      the CL field.</t>

      <t>3. SRv6 C-SID compression (NEXT &amp; REPLACE Flavor): using
      Arguments to carry multiple C-SIDs and the CL field.</t>

      <t/>

      <t>In addition, some new features are created, including network
      slicing<xref target="I-D.ietf-6man-enhanced-vpn-vtn-id"/>, IOAM<xref
      target="RFC9197"/>, Alternate Marking<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-alt-mark"/><xref
      target="I-D.fz-spring-srv6-alt-mark"/>, APN6<xref
      target="I-D.li-apn-ipv6-encap"/><xref target="I-D.li-apn-header"/>,
      DetNet<xref target="I-D.pthubert-detnet-ipv6-hbh"/>, etc.</t>

      <t>The instructions of these new features can be processed at:</t>

      <t>1. All nodes along a SR path: the instructions can be carried in the
      IPv6 Hop-by-Hop Options header (HBH).</t>

      <t>2. Endpoints of an SR path: the ones can be carried in the IPv6
      Destination Options Header (DOH) or the SRH TLV.</t>

      <t/>

      <t>In the second scenario, especially the second one, the usages of the
      options or TLVs will cause the following two issues:</t>

      <t>1. Lengthening the packet header, and reducing the transmission
      efficiency.</t>

      <t>2. Making the forwarding processing complex, affecting forwarding
      performance.</t>

      <t>Besides these issues, in the SRv6 C-SID compression (NEXT Flavor)
      solution, if all the C-SIDs of the SID list which should have been
      encapsulated in the SRH can be put in the IPv6 destination address of
      the packet, because there is no SRH or DOH before SRH any more after the
      compression there will be no space for the instructions which should
      have been encapsulated in the IPv6 SRH or Destination Options Header
      before SRH.</t>

      <t/>

      <t>In order to address these challenges, a feasible solution is to use
      the Arguments of the SRv6 SID to carry those instructions. Using SRv6
      Arguments to do that will bring following benefits:</t>

      <t>1. Reducing the needed space of IPv6 extension header or SRH TLV, so
      as to reduce the transmission overhead.</t>

      <t>2. SRv6 SID can reside in the IPv6 destination address field, so the
      SRv6 Arguments can be read and processed as a part of IPv6 address, from
      which the forwarding performance will benefit, because it avoids to
      process the extension header or SRv6 TLV behind the IPv6 header.</t>

      <t>3. Unify and simplify the processing: the instructions of both the
      SRv6 and the new features are all put in the Arguments part of SRv6 SID
      or IPv6 address.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Generalized Arguments">
      <t>In order to carry the instructions of multiple features in the SRv6
      Arguments, this section defines two methods to make the SRv6 Arguments
      generalized and structured to allocate spaces for the instructions.</t>

      <section title="Method A">
        <t>Network devices are configured a template for the purpose of
        parsing the SRv6 Arguments, and the devices read and process the
        content of the Arguments according to the template.</t>

        <t>The template defines what features are carried, and which bits they
        are used.</t>

        <t>For example, if the length of the Arguments is z bits and the
        number x, y, and z have the relationship 0&lt;x&lt;y&lt;z, then the
        template can define that:</t>

        <t>* The [0, x) bits carry the instructions of feature A;</t>

        <t>* The [x, y) bits carry the instructions of feature B;</t>

        <t>* The [y, z) bits carry the instructions of feature C.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Method B">
        <t>Define a bitmap in the Arguments, and each bit in the bitmap
        indicates whether the instructions of a specific feature exist. The
        correspondence of the bit and the feature, the length of the space of
        Arguments to carry the instructions for the feature, and the
        instructions needed to be carried for a specific feature can be
        defined further in a standardization way.</t>

        <t>The bitmap can be encoded from the most significant bit (MSB) or
        the least significant bit (LSB).</t>

        <t><figure align="left">
            <artwork><![CDATA[MSB:
    0               
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+------------------------------------
   |A|B|C|D|E|  the instructions of feature A~E
   +-+-+-+-+-+------------------------------------

LSB:
   ------------------------------------+-+-+-+-+-+
      the instructions of feature A~E  |A|B|C|D|E|
   ------------------------------------+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>When the bit is set (1), it indicates the instructions of the
        feature exist. If the bit is reset (0), there can be two options:</t>

        <t>Option 1: it indicates the instructions of the feature don't
        exist.</t>

        <t>Option 2: it indicates the instructions of the feature exist but is
        invalid.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Consideration of SRv6 C-SID Compression">
        <t>Since it is required to shift the C-SID in the SRv6 SID while
        applying the NEXT or NEXT &amp; REPLACE behavior for SRv6 C-SID
        compression, when method A or B is adopted, when C-SIDs are encoded in
        the generalized Arguments of the SRv6 SID which is used as the IPv6
        destination address, these C-SIDs MUST be placed from the most
        significant bit (MSB), that is, these C-SIDs MUST immediately
        following the LOC:FUNCT part of the SRv6 SID.</t>

        <t/>

        <t><figure align="left">
            <artwork><![CDATA[MSB:
    0               
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+------------------------------------
   |C-SID1 |C-SID2 |C-SIDn |A|B|C|D|E|  the instructions of feature A~E
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+------------------------------------

LSB:
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-----------------------------------+-+-+-+-+-+
   |C-SID1 |C-SID2 |C-SIDn |  the instructions of feature A~E  |A|B|C|D|E|
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-----------------------------------+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The remaining part of the generalized Arguments following the
        C-SIDs SHOULD NOT be shifted when C-SIDs part is shifted. This means
        the position of the remaining part after the C-SIDs in the generalized
        arguments SHOULD be fixed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Flavor for Generalized Arguments">
      <t>This section defines a new flavor to support processing the
      Generalized Arguments, named as Structured Arguments flavor.</t>

      <t>The pseudocode of the Structured Arguments flavor is as follows:</t>

      <t/>

      <t><figure align="left">
          <artwork><![CDATA[Method A:
S01. If (some NEXT-C-SIDs are encoded in the Generalized Arguments) {
S02.     Left shift the C-SIDs by the length of one C-SID
S03. }
S04. Load the relative template
S05. Parse the Generalized Arguments as per section 4.1
S06. For each parsed feature {
S07.     Perform actions according to the parsed instructions
         as per the specifications of that feature
S08. }

Method B:
S01. If (some NEXT-C-SIDs are encoded in the Generalized Arguments) {
S02.     Left shift the C-SIDs by the length of one C-SID
S03. }
S04. For each bit in the bitmap {
S05.     If (the bit == 1) {
S06.         Parse the instructions of the feature from the Generalized
             Arguments as per section 4.2
S07.         Perform actions according to the parsed instructions
             as per the specifications of that feature
S08.     }
S09. }

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3272"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-srh-compression'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-6man-enhanced-vpn-vtn-id'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9197"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8986"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8754"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-alt-mark'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.fz-spring-srv6-alt-mark'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-apn-header'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-apn-ipv6-encap'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.pthubert-detnet-ipv6-hbh'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
